Tatiana Fokina

Accessibility Engineer

Tbilisi, Georgia +9 000 000 000 UK Global Talent Visa Holder fokinatatian@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/tanya-fokina fokina-dev.ru

CPACC-certified Accessibility Engineer with 5+ years of Web/Frontend Development, specializing in developing user-centred interfaces.

Demonstrated proficiency in web technologies, including HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. Mastery of WAI-ARIA, WCAG, and ATAG standards and guidelines. Experienced with assistive technologies and testing tools.

Leadership in accessibility advocacy through public writing, speaking engagements and community initiatives.

Work experience

Doka Guide August 2022 – Present, remote

Editor, accessibility engineer, contributor.

- Architected a content plan, directed and launched the Accessibility section within a 3-month timeframe.
- Collaborated with 70+ contributors to develop 20+ articles on accessibility, 20+ materials on HTML and CSS, and 50+ on other web technologies.
- Crafted more than 100 articles on topics, such as accessibility, HTML, and CSS.
- Executed a WCAG-EM-based accessibility audit, resolving 29 issues on the project's website.

JUG Ru Group May 2019 – June 2020, St. Petersburg, Russia Frontend developer.

- Led accessibility audits on 10+ conference sites, improving Lighthouse accessibility scores by 48%.
- Maintained and modernized 10+ legacy projects, enchasing performance by 15% and ensured functionality for 5,000+ users
- Engineered 4 features for user accounts on the ticket platform in collaboration with designers, frontend, and backend developers, enhanced user experience and functionality.
- Co-developed a live streaming conference platform from concept to launch within a 2-month timespan.

Self-employment December 2016 – May 2019, St. Petersburg, Russia Freelance web developer.

- Conceptualized and implemented 7 landing pages and 3 multi-page sites for clients, strengthening their online presence.
- Developed 3 templates for MODX and Drupal, simplifying client content management processes.
- Remediated 5 websites to comply with government accessibility standards, reducing legal risks.

Skills

Core technologies. HTML5, JavaScript (ECMAScript 6), CSS3.

Advanced skills. TypeScript, Angular, Next.js, Sass/SCSS, Stylus, Pug, Nunjacks.

Standards and legislation. WAI-ARIA 1.2, WCAG 2.2, ATAG 2.0, WCAG-EM 1.0, Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), Section 508, Equality Act 2010, EN 301 549, Web Accessibility Directive (WAD), European Accessibility Act (EAA).

Assistive technologies. NVDA, JAWS, VoiceOver, TalkBack, Microsoft Magnifier, ZoomText.

Tools and platforms. Git, GitHub, GitLab, axe DevTools, Wave Evaluation Tool (WAVE), Accessibility Insights, Pa11y, accessibility bookmarklets, Storybook, 11ty, Gulp, Figma.

Education

St. Petersburg State Institute of Culture June 2015, St. Petersburg, Russia Specialist's degree in Integrated Library Systems (ILS).

Other

Courses and certificates. Practical Accessibility course, <u>CPACC</u>, Trusted Tester (v5.1.3).

Community experience. Google's Women Techmakers ambassador (WTM); host <u>Inclusive</u> <u>Pineapple</u> podcast; organizer of <u>pitera11y_meetup</u> and Doka Guide meetup.

Publications and talks. Translation of <u>Accessibility Myths project</u>; post <u>Understanding Skip Links</u> on professional blog; article <u>What Are ARIA Live Regions</u> on Doka Guide; talk <u>Accessibility and Typography</u> at Tbilisi A11y & UX Day.